Guide to the Lawrence A. Wien Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Lawrence A. Wien Papers,
1954-1982
Wien, Lawrence A., 1905-1988.
57.5 linear ft. (ca. 57,500 items in 125 boxes & 1 oversize folder).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library 6th floor, New York, NY 10027.
4079665
Biographical Note
Trustee, Columbia University, 1966-1972 (Columbia B.A., 1925; LLB, 1927). Philanthropist, lawyer and entrepreneur.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, documents, financial records and memorabilia. The personal correspondence of Lawrence A. Wien, 1960-1983; including memoirs and notes on interests both personal and financial. The Lawrence A. Wien Foundation files include correspondence, 1958-1976, information on the Foundation's 10-year trust, and information on tax returns. Files for the Charles and Rosanna Batchelor Memorial fund consist of general correspondence, grant requests, and miscellaneous financial documents. The Committee to Increase Corporate Philanthropic Giving files comprise a large part of the collection. Among the numerous individual corporations represented are the American Broadcasting Company and the Zale Company. Wien's Foundation for the Improvement of Housing Arrangements for Official Foreign Personnel has personal files for each person receiving the Foundation's benefits, guarantees for those individuals, and letters ment to solicit funds from various corporations.
In addition to information on other philanthropic interests, the collection contains Wien's dealings with Brandeis University, including correspondence, estate records, and folders on investors in the Wien International Scholarship Program (WISP). There are also Columbia University files including correspondence, 1967-1975, investment schedules for Wien's
There are also Columbia University files including correspondence, 1967-1975, investment schedules for Wien's Scholarship program at the Columbia Law School, and several lottery tickets in connection with his philanthropy to Columbia. Wiens's interests in the media and perfroming arts are represented in files on the Educational Broadcasting Corporation, Institute of International Education, and various dramatic productions he sponsored, including "Fiddler on the Roof," "Music Man," and "Zorba the Greek," as well as his dealings with Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts. Also included is material on his involvement in the construction of the Apestuck Golf Club and his term as a Con Edison trustee. The collection also contains some personal memorabilia.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 14 series:
Series I: Personal Files
Series II: L. A. Wien Foundation, Inc. Files
Series III: Charles and Rosanna Batchelor Memorial, Inc. Files
Series IV: Committee to Increase Corporate Philanthropic Giving Files
Series V: Foundation for Improvement of Housing Arrangements for Official Foreign
Series VI: Miscellaneous Philanthropic Interests Files
Series VII: Brandeis University Files
Series VIII: Columbia University Files
Series IX: Miscellaneous Studies and Publications
Series X: Performing Arts (Individual Productions) Files
Series XI: Lincoln Center Files
Series XII: Apestuck Golf Club Construction Corp. Files
Series XIII: Con Edison's Summary Reports to Trustees Files
Series XIV: Memorabilia
Subjects
Columbia University.; Consolidated Edison Company of New York, inc.; Institute of International Education (New York, N.Y.); Brandeis University.; Federation of Jewish Philanthropies of New York.; Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts.; Charities.; Endowments.; Scholarships.; Philanthropists.; Musical theater.; Charitable giving.; Albums.; Annual reports.; Applications.; Bills (financial).; Certificates.; Directories.; Financial records.; Insurance policies.; Invitations.; Leases.; Memorabilia.; Minutes.; Photographs.; Plaques.; Prospectuses.; Reports.; Speeches.; Stock certificates.; Tax returns.; Tickets.; Benefactors.; Businessmen.; College trustees.; Lawyers.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
03/30/1990 M-90-03-30 Wien, Lawrence A. (Bequest of the Estate) Bequest
Bequest of the Estate of Lawrence A. Wien, 1990.
- Series I: Personal Files
  - Subseries I.1: Personal Correspondence, 1960 - 1982
    - January 1, 1960 - July 31, 1961 (Box 1)
    - August 1, 1961 - December 31, 1962 (Box 2)
    - January 1, 1963 - December 31, 1964 (Box 3)
    - 1965 - 1966 (Box 4)
    - 1967 (Box 5)
    - 1968 (Box 6)
    - 1971 - 1972 (Box 7)
    - 1973, 1976 (Box 8)
    - 1977 - 1978 (Box 9)
    - Jan 1, 1979 - July 31, 1980 (Box 10)
    - August 1, 1980 - April 30, 1982 (Box 11)
    - 70th Birthday Celebration (Box 11)
    - 80th Birthday Celebration (Box 11)
    - Personal Files: Subjects A – Z:
      - Academic Consulting Assoc. (Box 12)
      - Biographical Summary (Box 12)
      - Casualty Losses (Box 12)
      - Change of Address (Box 12)
      - Compensation Injury to Micheal Samuelman (Box 12)
      - Group Life Insurance (Box 12)
      - "Humphrey for President" (1968) (Box 12)
      - Investments (Mr. Wien Papers) (Box 12)
      - London, England (Box 12)
      - correspondence and lease (Box 12)
      - Net Worth (Box 12)
      - Plaza Hotel (Assoc. & Party) (Box 12)
      - Rapidata, Inc. (Box 12)
      - Sale of Wien's Theater Interests (Box 12)
      - Stock Certificates (Warwick) (Box 12)
      - Subscriptions (Box 12)
      - Elsie Yingere Loans (Box 12)
    - Tax Records/Paid Bills 1961 - 1974 etc. (Box 13)
- Series II: L. A. Wien Foundation, Inc. Files
  - Correspondence, 1958–1976
    - 1958 – 1961 (Box 14)
    - 1962 – 1966 (Box 15)
    - 1967 - 1968 (Box 16)
    - 1969 - 1972 (Box 17)
    - 1973 - 1976 (Box 18)
    - Files (Box 19)
    - Ten Year Trust Information (Box 20)
    - Tax Returns (Box 21)
    - NYS Registration (Box 21)
- Series III: Charles and Rosanna Batchelor Memorial, Inc. Files
  - General Correspondence, 1961 - 1971 (Box 22)
  - Annual Report of Charitable Organization Dissolution (Box 22)
  - Financial Statements, Reports on 1967 Grant (Box 23)
  - Grants Requested Since 1967 (w/ no Action) (Box 23)
  - Investment Review (Box 23)
  - Membership Certificate (Box 23)
  - Minutes (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
  - Income Tax (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Financial (Box 24)
- Series IV: Committee to Increase Corporate Philanthropic Giving Files
  - * Individual Corporation Folders, A - Z*
    - Abbot Laboratories - American Brands, Inc. (Box 25)
    - American Broadcasting Co. - American Natural Resources Co. (Box 26)
    - American Standard, Inc. - Asarco, Inc. (Box 27)
    - Ashland Oil, Inc. - Baker International Co. (Box 28)
    - Bankamerica Co. - Belco Petroleum, Inc. (Box 29)
    - Bendix Co. - Borden, Inc. (Box 30)
    - Briggs and Stratton Co. - Carnation Co. (Box 31)
    - Carpenter Technology Co. - Cheesebrough-Pond's, Inc. (Box 32)
    - Cities Service Co. - Colt Industries, Inc. (Box 33)
    - Commonwealth Edison Co. - Continental Telephone Co. (Box 34)
    - Continental Oil Co. (Conoco) - Data General Co. (Box 35)
    - Deere & Co. - Duke Power Co. (Box 36)
    - Dun & Bradstreet Co. - Ex-Cell-O Co. (Box 37)
    - Exxon Co. - Foremost McKesson, Inc. (Box 38)
    - Freeport-McMoran, Inc. - General Mills, Inc. (Box 39)
    - General Motors Co. - Goodrich (B. F.) Co. (Box 40)
    - Grace (W. R.) & Co. - Heinz (H. J.) Co. (Box 41)
    - Hercules, Inc. - Hughes Tool Co. (Box 42)
    - Humana, Inc. - International Harvester Co. (Box 43)
    - International Minerals & Chemical Co. - Kemper Co. (Box 44)
    - Kerr-McGee Co. - Louisiana Land & Exploration Co. (Box 45)
    - Louisiana Pacific Co. - Marathon Oil Co. (Box 46)
    - Marriott Co. - Minnesota Mining & Manufacturing Co. (Box 47)
    - Missouri Pacific Co. - Murphy Oil Co. (Box 48)
    - Nabisco Brands, Inc. - NL Industries, Inc. (Box 49)
    - NLT Co. - Owens-Illinois, Inc. (Box 50)
    - Pacific Northwest Bell Telephone Co. - Phillips Petroleum Co. (Box 51)
    - Pillsbury Co. - Raytheon Co. (Box 52)
    - RCA Co. - Richardson-Vicks, Inc. (Box 53)
    - Rockwell International Co. - SCM Co. (Box 54)
    - Scott Paper Co. - Southern Co. (Box 55)
    - Southern Natural Resources Co. - Standard Oil Co. (Ohio) (Box 56)
    - Stauffer Chemical Co. - Tenneco, Inc. (Box 57)
    - Texaco, Inc. - Transco Companies, Inc. (Box 58)
    - TRW, Inc. - United Technologies Co. (Box 59)
    - United Telecommunications, Inc. - West Point-Pepperell, Inc. (Box 60)
    - Weyerhaeuser - Zale Co. (Box 61)
    - General Correspondence (Box 61)
    - Business Roundtable (Box 61)
    - FQ Churchill Workpapers (Box 61)
    - Procedure regarding submission of proposals (Box 62)
    - Progress Reports, Folders 1-24 (Box 62)
    - Reports and Summaries (Box 63)
    - Statistical Summary Report (Box 63)
    - FQC's Worksheets re Summary Reports (Box 63)
    - Various Speeches (copies) (Box 63)
- Series V: Foundation for Improvement of Housing Arrangements for Official Foreign
  - *Personnel, Inc. Files*
    - Abdul-Lateef - Braithwaite (Box 64)
    - Budin - Elhussein (Box 65)
    - Elmi - Kombele (Box 66)
    - Lee - Rakotosihinaka (Box 67)
    - Rocos - Zahran (Box 68)
    - Guarantee Letters, Folders 40-45, 47-48 (Box 69)
    - Guarantee Letters, Folders 49-56 (Box 70)
    - Guarantee Letters, Folders 57-66 (Box 71)
    - Guarantee Letters, Folders 67-74, 80 (Box 72)
    - Solicitation File (Box 73)
    - Solicitation Letters, 1974 (Box 73)
- Series VI: Miscellaneous Philanthropic Interests Files
  - Brotherhood House (Box 74)
  - Canisius College (Box 74)
  - Girls' Town (Box 74)
  - Georgetown Montrose Interest (Mae Wien) (Box 74)
  - Greater New York Fund (Box 74)
  - Minimax Supermarkets SpA, Roma, Italia (Box 75)
  - New York City Council Against Poverty (Box 75)
  - Pro Deo University (Box 75)
  - Promercantil, S.A. (Box 75)
  - Slifka, Alan and Jacqueline (Box 75)
  - Stylon Corporation (Box 75)
- Series VII: Brandeis University Files
  - General Correspondence, 1967 (Box 76)
  - General Correspondence, 1/1/68 - 9/30/69 (Box 77)
  - General Correspondence, 10/1/69-12/31/69,1971,1973-1975 (Box 78)
  - Wien International Scholarship Program (WISP) (Box 79)
  - General Correspondence 1962-1967, 1969, 1971-1977 (Box 79)
  - Records of Estates (Box 80)
  - Berglas - Irving (Box 80)
  - Records of Estates (Box 81)
  - Kott - Robinson (Box 81)
  - Records of Estates (Box 82)
  - Rosenbaum - Sabath (Box 82)
  - Records of Estates (Box 83)
  - Schulman - Wolf (Box 83)
  - Wien International Scholarship Program (WISP) (Box 84)
  - Deficit Fund, Luncheons 60 East Club (Box 84)
  - Pooled Income Fund (Box 84)
  - Joslin, Archie O. -- Gift (Box 84)
  - Student Applications (Box 84)
  - Summer Job Program (Box 84)
  - Investors (Box 84)
  - Baton Rouge Motor Lodge Assoc. - Dyckman Hotel Assoc. (Box 84)
  - WISP Investors (Box 85)
  - Dyckman Hotel Assoc. - Empire State Building Assoc. (Box 85)
  - WISP Investors (Box 86)
  - Empire State Building Assoc. - Graybar Assoc. (Box 86)
  - WISP Investors (Box 87)
  - Graybar Assoc. - 108 E. 38th Street Assoc. (Box 87)
  - WISP Investors (Box 88)
  - 108 E. 38th Street Assoc. - Senator Hotel Assoc. (Box 88)
  - WISP Investors (Box 89)
  - Senator Hotel Assoc. - 250 W. 57th St. Assoc. (Box 89)
  - WISP Investors (Box 90)
  - 250 W. 57th St. Assoc. - Warwick Hotel Assoc. (Box 90)
  - Advisory Council on University Affairs (Box 91)
  - Minutes (Box 91)
  - Blank Assignments (Box 91)
  - David Squire (Box 91)
  - Blank Assignments (Box 92)
  - David Squire (Box 92)
  - Gifts (Box 92)
  - Correspondence (Box 92)
  - Agreements (Box 92)
  - Planning and Development Council (Box 92)
  - Minutes (Box 92)
  - Miscellaneous Directories (Box 92)
  - Miscellaneous Material (Box 93)
- Series VIII: Columbia University Files
  - General Correspondence, 1967 - 1975 (Box 94)
  - Student Applications (1967-1976) (Box 95)
  - Appraisal of Land (Box 95)
  - Columbia College Council - Misc. (Box 96)
  - Committee on Finance/Committee on Development of Alumni Affairs (Box 96)
  - Financial Reports (1967-1968) (Box 96)
  - Gymnasium Building Fund (Box 96)
  - Law School Solicitations (Box 96)
  - Lottery Tickets (NY) In Connection w/ CU (Box 96)
  - President's Report to Trustees (Box 96)
  - Scholarship Program at Columbia Law School (Fund) (Box 97)
  - General Correspondence, 1963-1975 (Box 97)
  - Schedule of Investments (Box 97)
  - Baton Rouge Motor Lodge Assoc. - Dyckman Hotel Assoc. (Box 97)
  - Scholarship Program at Columbia Law School Investments (Box 98)
  - Empire State Building Assoc. - Stewart Ave. Assoc. (Box 98)
  - Scholarship Program (Fund) at Law School Investments (Box 99)
  - Sterick-Memphis Realty Co. - Warwick Hotel Assoc. (Box 99)
  - Temple Committee (Box 99)
  - Trustees' Committee on Development and Alumni Affairs (Box 99)
  - University Senate, Proposal for Establishment of..(Exec. Committee (Box 99)
  - of Faculty) (Box 99)
- Series IX: Miscellaneous Studies and Publications
  - Educational Broadcasting Corp., Ch. 13 Files
    - General Correspondence, 1966 (Box 100)
    - Minutes (Box 100)
    - Sample of 1966 Mailing (first name Basis) (Box 100)
  - Institute of International Education Files
    - General Correspondence 1966-1969 (Box 101)
    - Advertising Agreements (Box 101)
    - Educational Policies Committee (Box 101)
    - Lists for IIE Luncheon (Box 101)
    - Message Released to Congress, Feb 2, 1966 (Box 101)
    - Minutes (Box 101)
    - Ten Year Plan (Box 101)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 101)
- Series X: Performing Arts (Individual Productions) Files
  - "Case for Satan" (Box 102)
  - "Company" Company (Box 102)
  - "Cry For Us All" (L. M. Company) (Box 102)
  - "Fiddler on the Roof" (Box 102)
  - Partnership Interests, Fin. Reports (Box 102)
  - "The Fighting Cock" (The Hurlu Co.) (Box 102)
  - "Fiorello" Co. (Box 102)
  - Correspondence and Agreements
    - "Follies" Co. (Box 103)
    - "Kuprin" Co. (Box 103)
    - "Love and Kisses" (Box 103)
    - "Music Man" (Box 103)
    - "Nowhere to Go But Up" (Box 104)
    - "Passage to India" (Box 104)
    - Playwrights - Multiplay Co. (Box 104)
    - "Poor Bitos" (Box 104)
    - "She Loves Me"...incl. British vers. (Box 104)
    - "Something About a Soldier" (Box 104)
    - "Subways Are For Sleeping" (Box 104)
    - "A Swim in the Sea" (Box 104)
    - "Tenderloin" (Box 104)
    - "The Tenth Man" (Formerly "The Dybuk" Company) (Box 105)
    - Financial Statements and Assignment (Box 105)
    - "West Side Story" (Box 105)
    - Correspondence and Misc. (Box 105)
    - "Zorba the Greek" (Box 105)
    - Correspondence, Financial Statements (Box 105)
    - Prospectives (Box 105)
- Series XI: Lincoln Center Files
  - Correspondence, 1964-1968 (Box 106)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 107)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1977 (Box 108)
  - General File (Box 109)
  - Board of Directors (Box 109)
  - Charter Assoc.'s Annual Letters (Box 109)
  - Committee on Education (incl. Minutes) (Box 109)
  - Liquor License Application (Box 109)
  - Reports and Misc. (Box 109)
  - Revlon Foundation (Charles H. Revson) (Box 109)
  - Summary of Current Solicitations and Assignments (Box 109)
- Series XII: Apestuck Golf Club Construction Corp. Files
  - General Correspondence, 1967-July 31, 1973 (Box 110)
  - General Correspondence, 8/1/73-9/30/74 (Box 111)
  - Board of Governors (Box 111)
  - Contract Documents (Constr. Specifications) (Box 111)
  - Letter to James Ganley, Re: Employment (Box 111)
  - Assignment of Loan, by Wien, to Helmsley-Spear, Inc. (Box 111)
  - Helmsley-Wien 25th Anniversary Celebration Sale (Box 112)
  - Helmsley-Spear Installment of Golf Course Note (Box 112)
  - Invitations, 1968 (Box 112)
  - MBC File (Box 112)
  - Minutes (Box 112)
  - President's Trophy, Plaques for Sculpture (Box 112)
  - Promissory Notes, etc. (Box 112)
  - Prospective Members; Misc. (Box 112)
- Series XIII: Con Edison's Summary Reports to Trustees Files
  - December 1969 - February 1971 (Box 113)
  - June 1971 - January 1973 (Box 114)
  - February 1973 - July 1976 (sporadically) (Box 115)
- Series XIV: Memorabilia
  - Placque (oversize Folder) (Box 115)
  - Photo Album: Lawrence A. Wien's Activities as Columbia Trustee, 1971 (Box 115)